<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preacht at St. George's Church at Windsor Septemb. 27. 1685. By Edward Pelling, chaplain to his Grace the Duke of Somerset. Printed by order.</title>
            <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70775</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1099A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23220</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834841</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834841</idno>
            <idno type="VID">39423</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70775)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39423)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 727:21, 1956:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preacht at St. George's Church at Windsor Septemb. 27. 1685. By Edward Pelling, chaplain to his Grace the Duke of Somerset. Printed by order.</title>
                  <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Sam. Keble, at the Turks Head in Fleet-street, and Walter Davis, in Amen Corner,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a preliminary imprimatur leaf, possibly printed as E4.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery ("Early English books, 1641-1700" reel 727, identified as Wing P1099), and the Bodleian Library (reel 1956).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:39423:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39423:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A SERMON Preacht at St. <hi>GEORGE'S</hi> Church AT WINDSOR, <hi>Septemb.</hi> 27. 1685.</p>
            <p>By EDWARD PELLING, Chaplain to his Grace the Duke of <hi>Somerſet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed by Order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Sam. Keble,</hi> at the <hi>Turks Head</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> and <hi>Walter Davis,</hi> in <hi>Amen Corner.</hi> 1685.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:39423:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:39423:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached at St. <hi>GEORGE'S</hi> Church AT WINDSOR, <hi>Septemb.</hi> 27. 1685.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1 PET. 3. 13.</bibl>
                  <p>And who is he that will harm you, if ye be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of that which is good.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT may ſeem very ſtrange, that words to this purpoſe ſhould drop from St. <hi>Peters</hi> mouth; if we underſtand them ſo, as if good Men could not be intreated after an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil manner. For the whole Hiſtory of thoſe times wherein the Apoſtles lived, contradict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this Aſſertion, if we take it Univerſally, and at large. <hi>Stephen</hi> had been already ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and at the ſame time a great perſecution was raiſed againſt the Church at <hi>Jeruſalem, Act.</hi> 8. <hi>James</hi> the Brother of <hi>John</hi> was killed, and St. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf had been committed to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:39423:3"/> Priſon, <hi>Act</hi> 12. And how many ſorts of ill uſage did <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> and the reſt receive at the hands of Infidels, in thoſe times? Nay, our Apoſtle himſelf ſuppoſeth that good men might ſuffer for their righteouſneſs, at the Verſe immediately following my Text; <hi>But and if ye ſuffer for Righteouſneſs ſake, happy are ye,</hi> and ſo on. Either then we muſt deny plain matters of Fact; or elſe we muſt ſuppoſe the Chriſtians of thoſe times not to have been followers of that which is good; or elſe we muſt conclude that St. <hi>Peter</hi> had in this Place a further meaning, beſides that which lyeth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to our firſt view.</p>
            <p>Therefore in diſcourſing upon this portion of Scripture, I ſhall</p>
            <p n="1">1. Shew what is the full and genuine ſenſe of the words.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Demonſtrate the Truth of that, which St. <hi>Peter</hi> doth here intend.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And ſo, in the third place, bring down the whole to our own Practice, with reſpect to thoſe Circumſtances which we our ſelves are in at this preſent juncture.</p>
            <p>As to the Firſt, the Apoſtles meaning muſt needs be this; that none will hurt us, if they have a true reſpect for Vertue and Goodneſs, as long as they <hi>ſee</hi> us follow that which is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and manifeſtly good; as long as they are <hi>ſatisfied,</hi> and <hi>convinced</hi> of our Integrity; as long as we diſcharge our Reputation as well as our Conſciences; as long as our Light ſo ſhineth before men, that they ſee our good works,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:39423:3"/> and cannot but confeſs, that of a Truth our Converſation is honeſt and upright, and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Si ſemper ea quae Planè bona ſunt imitemini;</hi> Grot. <hi>in</hi> Loc.</note> in every reſpect, ſuch as doth become the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Chriſts Religion. Sometimes it is not enough for us to be innocent, unleſs our Innocence doth <hi>appear,</hi> ſo that we may be able to ſtop the mouths, and put to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men, if their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads be but tollerably tender. It was the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry caſe of Chriſtians in the Apoſtolical Age<hi>:</hi> Though Piety and Vertue was the great care and imployment of their Lives; though they valued a good Conſcience above the whole World, yet ſtrangers to the Faith were every where miſtaken in them, and 'twas a long time before they could conquer thoſe ſtrong preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices they had entertained againſt them. The <hi>Jews</hi> on the one hand lookt upon them as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novators and Hereticks: Though their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was not any new thing, but a Reformation of thoſe abuſes which had crept into the Church <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Euſeb. Hiſt. Eccleſ. lib 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> by degrees, yet their new Name gave offence (for they were firſt called Chriſtians at <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och)</hi> and their Enemies believed that their Faith was New alſo. Where was your Religion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt? As thoſe ſuperſtitious people were ready to object. They were angry at the ſuppoſed Novelty of the Chriſtian Religion; though if that was a Reproach to the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>then,</hi> that it was of ſo <hi>late</hi> a date, the quarrel ſeem'd to be with God himſelf, becauſe he ſent not his Son <hi>ſooner</hi> into the World. On the other hand, the <hi>Pagans</hi> lookt upon the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:39423:4"/> followers of Jeſus as a ſeditious ſort of men, that carried on an intereſt in oppoſition to the Intereſt of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire? Chriſt himſelf was reviled as <hi>Caeſars</hi> Enemy; and his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples had the Character of people that turned the World upſide down, that did all things contrary to the decrees of <hi>Caeſar, Act,</hi> 17. Many violent prejudices were againſt them, and the generality of people ran away with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of groſs miſtakes concerning them and their Religion, which nothing but time and Patience could poſſibly Remove. And therefore St. <hi>Peters</hi> buſineſs in the Text was, to perſwade them, not only to be followers of that which was Good (for ſo they were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready) but moreover to give all poſſible De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of their integrity. And that this was the Apoſtles ſenſe appears clearly from thoſe words, but three Verſes after my Text, that whereas men ſpeak Evil of you, as of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil doers, they may be aſhamed that falſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe your Good Converſation in Chriſt. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could make their Enemies aſhamed, but Notoriety of fact; the way to make them bluſh was to let them ſee what horrible miſtakes they were under; then they would be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, when 'twas made clear and apparent, how <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoc ipſum eis pudori erit, ubi apparuerit ex factis veſtris quàm recta et pura ſit Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana Religio.</hi> Grot. <hi>in</hi> 1 Pet. 3. 16.</note> Right and pure the Chriſtian Religion was; as the learned <hi>Grotius</hi> hath noted upon that place.</p>
            <p>So that the full meaning of the Apoſtle here, is this, that when once we give plain and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable Proofs that we are really follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:39423:4"/> of that which is Good; when once we make it clear and evident to the World, ſo that all Men of ſenſe and common honeſty muſt needs grant that we are ſo, we have reaſon enough to believe then that all things will go very well with us; eſpecially when ſuch as are a terrour to evil doers, domot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>act upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mean, any diſhonourable, any baſe deſigns, but profeſs a due regard, and love for good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and therefore cannot be rationally ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be willing at any time to afflict it, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be unfortunately upon miſinformation and miſtakes; which was indeed the caſe of the Primitive Chriſtians; but cannot be ours now, unleſs the fault be our own firſt.</p>
            <p>2. The ſenſe of the Text being thus clear'd, I proceed, in the ſecond place, to Demonſtrate the Truth of the thing. And for the clearing of that too, many arguments might be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to your conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As, Firſt, concerning the good Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, which never faileth ſuch good men, as conſcientiouſly and honeſtly act in ſubſerviency to the Honour and Intereſt of true Religion. And when all is done, that lyeth in the power of Second and ſubordinate Cauſes, The Providence of God is the onely certain and infallible ſecurity we may depend upon with confidence. Every thing in the World but Providence, is uncertain and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingent: 'Tis this that is the great ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for all Societies, States, and Kingdoms to truſt to; nay the only ſtabilement, the whole
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:39423:5"/> frame of the Univerſe depends upon, which without this Prop and Stay, had been long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go ſhattered into its Primordial Chaos. So that when men of Atheiſtical Spirits laugh at us as a ſort of credulous and eaſie people, for ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting our ſelves upon Providence in all Caſes; Our anſwer is not more religious than 'tis ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, that we truſt to that which hath hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to preſerved and ſupported the whole world.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Beſides, Secondly, there is in all men ſuch an operative and ſtirring Principle (common to Mankind, becauſe fixt and radicated in our common nature) that tho Goodneſs may ſeem ſomewhat hard in its practice, yet 'tis very pleaſant and lovely to the Eye; and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more apt either to be commended, or protected by thoſe, who under God do ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intend the affairs of the World; eſpecially by thoſe whoſe Spirits are refined from the Fecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of ſavage and <hi>ſordid</hi> natures; whoſe Souls are truly generous and <hi>great;</hi> whoſe tempers are <hi>humane;</hi> and who go upon Principles of Honour; tho their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may be poſſeſt with ſeveral Notions that are different from other mens. <hi>Tiberius</hi> was none of the beſt of thoſe Roman Emperours that were Heathen, and yet we are told by <hi>Tertullian,</hi> who was ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently skilled in the Laws <note place="margin">Tiberius <hi>cuius tempore nomen Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianum in ſeculum introivit, annuncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſibi ex</hi> Syria Paleſtina <hi>quae illic veritatem ipſius divinitatis revelave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laverat, detulit ad Senatum cum prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogativa Suffragii ſui.</hi> Tertul. Apol. c. 5.</note> and Hiſtory of <hi>Rome,</hi> that when <hi>Tiberius</hi> heard of the Miracles which had been done by our bleſſed Saviour, and was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:39423:5"/> conſtrained to believe that he was both a good man, and a divine Perſon, he moved the Senate, that Chriſt might be put into the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of their Gods. Some ſay, that <hi>Pilate</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide Laurent. de la Barre An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notat. in</hi> Tertul. Apolog.</note> ſent the Emperour an account of the works and innocence of the bleſſed Jeſus, and tho' <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> excuſed the Judgment he had given againſt him, being <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quibus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſionibuo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductus ipſe, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem querelis eorum adhibui,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ep. Pilati.</hi>
               </note> impoſed upon and deceived by the Jews, yet <hi>Tiberius</hi> condemned him to death be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had any hand at all in the death of Chriſt. Which Story, if it be true, is an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that if <hi>Tiberius</hi> himſelf had been then in <hi>Pilates</hi> place, he, tho an Heathen, would have protected our Lords innocence, who was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſuch a friend to his memory. This is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that <hi>Pilate</hi>'s wife ſent importunately to him as he ſat upon the Judgment-Seat, to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all bloody proceedings againſt our Lord, becauſe ſhe was ſatisfied that he was a Juſt Man (for ſo ſhe called him, S. <hi>Matth.</hi> 27. 19.) 'Twas the ſenſe of our Saviours innocency, that made that woman ſo earneſtly to interpoſe, tho ſhe was guided only by natural Conſcience.</p>
            <p>But it is not time for me yet to meddle with the Hiſtory of thoſe firſt Ages of Chriſtianity. It is a paſſage, that caſually fell under my hands; and it confirms a little this obſervable Truth, that ſubſtantial and ſolid Vertue never ſuffers in any high degree, where 'tis throughly known and diſcovered; unleſs by chance and by ſome ſpecial permiſſion of God it ſuffers at the hands of ſome anomalous Creature, ſome monſtrous Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of a Man (as <hi>Pilate</hi> was) that has caſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:39423:6"/> off all regard to Humanity, and Honour, and true Greatneſs, as well as bid defiance to all manner of Religion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I might add, in the third place, that the following of that which is Good (eſpecially if we follow it ſo as our Saviour did, and as he hath chalked out the way to us) hath ſuch a Natural Tendency to Promote; even the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular advantages and wellfare of all Mankind, that few who underſtand, none that value their own Intereſt, will be either ſo Ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, or ſo Impolitick, and ſo much enemies to themſelves, as to injure Men whoſe Principles and Practices apparently tend to the common Good of All. Such is the Nature of thoſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Virtues, which our Lord hath left us to tranſcribe, that no other Inſtitution what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever can ſerve more to the Advantage, or ſo much to the Quiet and Peace of the World, as our Religion doth, when 'tis Conſcientiouſly and Honeſtly obſerved. We are bound to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Peace as well as Holineſs; to love one another, and even our implacable Enemies; to ſtudy to be Quiet, to do every Man his own Buſineſs, and to abide in his own Calling; not to do Evil, though for Good ends; but to commit our ſelves to God in Well-doing; to be Humble, Gentle, and Meek; to pay Tribute to whom Tribute is due, and Honour to whom Honour; to give to <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caeſars,</hi> as well as to God the things that are Gods, to be ſubject to Principalities and Powers; to obey Magiſtrates; and to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:39423:6"/> not onely for wrath, but alſo (and chiefly) for Conſcience ſake. <hi>And who is he that will harm</hi> us, if we be found to <hi>be followers of that which is Good,</hi> according to theſe Meaſures and Rules? He is the Miniſter of God to us for Good, ſaith the Scripture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 4. And if Experience tells him, that we are Servants to him for his Good too, we have no reaſon to fear the Edge of that Sword, which is never drawn to cut off a Friend.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But for the full proof of this Aſſertion in my Text, that none will harm us, if we be known to be followers of that which is Good, I ſhall take leave to ſearch a little into the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the Primitive Ages, and Examine how Matters went with Chriſtians in thoſe Times, as often as they made it appear that they were fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of that which was Good. For if it can be proved, that as they cleared their Integrity, ſo they found Eaſe, and Encouragements, even under a Heathen Government, there can be no room for any inordinate Jealouſies among Us, whoſe Lot (God be bleſſed) is fallen in a Religious and Chriſtian ſtate, if we be careful to acquit our ſelves to the whole World, by diſcharging our duty with Fidelity and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, as the Ancient Chriſtians did theirs.</p>
            <p>Now nothing can be clearer out of the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of all the Old Apologiſts for Chriſtianity, than that the <hi>Pagans</hi> were infinitely miſtaken in their Opinions of the Church, and that they uſed the Members of it hardly upon thoſe wrong Preſumptions: To Rectifie theſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:39423:7"/> and ſo to make their Enemies to be at Peace with them, the Doctors of the Church deſired nothing more, than that the Emperors would pleaſe to Examine their Doctrines and Manners: They wondred at the Raſhneſs of their Tormentors; and laid the blame of their violent and unjuſt proceedings upon their groſs <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dolemus de Ignorantia ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra, &amp;c.</hi> Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tull. <hi>ad</hi> Scapu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam. <hi>Ita utrum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ex alterutro re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darguimus, &amp; Ignorare illos dum oderunt, &amp; injuſtè odiſſè dum ignorant.</hi> Id <hi>Apolog. adv. Gentes. Cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Illud ſolum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectatur, quod Odio publico ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarium eſt, Confeſſio Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, non Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio criminis.</hi> Tert. <hi>Lib. Supr.</hi>
               </note> Ignorance: For they were tortured for the ſake of their Name, becauſe they called themſelves Chriſtians; the <hi>Pagans</hi> enquiring no further, whether they were Thieves or Rebels or any other Criminals in the Eye of the Laws, but taking all for granted, that the Wickedneſs of Men could lay to their charge. This was a very hard caſe; yet thoſe Excellent Chriſtians ſubmitted to it with Patience and Chearfulneſs, hoping that in time the Experience of their Enemies would convince them, and engage them to be favourable to Chriſtianity. And 'tis very Remarkable and Appoſite to our purpoſe what <hi>Tertullian</hi> obſerved, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Teſtimonium ignoran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ae eſt, quae iniquitatem dum excuſat, condemnat; cum omnes qui retrò oderant, quia ignorabant quale eſſet quod oderant, ſimul ut deſinant ignorare, deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent &amp; Odiſſe.</hi> Tert. Apol. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> that all thoſe who had hated Chriſtianity, becauſe they knew not what it was, as ſoon as ever their Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance was Removed, their Hatred ceaſed alſo; This is a plain Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of what I am novv ſhevving, that vvhen good Men acquit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves vvell to the World, it ever goes vvell vvith them: But for our plenary ſatisfaction in this point, let us look a little into ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular inſtances.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:39423:7"/>
            <p> The firſt that rais'd a general <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Orientem fidem</hi> Romae <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> Nero <hi>cruentavit,</hi> Tertul. <hi>in</hi> Scorpia <hi>Vide &amp;</hi> Apol. cap. 5.</note> Storm againſt the Church was <hi>Nero.</hi> But tho he was infamous for his San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinary and barbarous temper, yet to me it ſeems manifeſt that his cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Afflicti ſuppliciis Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni; genus hominum ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis novae ac malificae,</hi> Suet. <hi>in</hi> Nerone, Sect. 16.<hi>—Quos per flagitia inviſos, vulgus Chriſtianos appellabat,</hi> Tacit. Annal. lib. 15.<hi>—Exitialis ſuperſtitio,</hi> id. ibid.</note> were grounded upon his perfect ignorance of the Chriſtians Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence; for they were repreſented then as people of a new and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheivous Religion (as <hi>Suetonius</hi> ſaid) as a deadly and pernicious Sect (ſaith <hi>Tacitus)</hi> that were generally hated; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>—Haud perinde in crimine incendii, quàm odio Humani generis convicti ſunt.</hi> Tacit. i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid.</note> and therefore the fitteſt (as the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour thought) to have the guilt of burning the City of <hi>Rome</hi> fixed upon them. Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly they were abuſed (as I obſerved before out of the Acts of the Apoſtles) as Movers of Sedition, and enemies of the Roman Empire: The belief whereof paſt currantly at <hi>Rome,</hi> where they made no diſtinction between Chriſtians and Jews, becauſe Chriſtianity came out of <hi>Judea;</hi> and conſidering how reſtleſs, facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ungovernable the Jews had been, not onely in the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Joſ. Scaligeri <hi>animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. in</hi> Euſeb. Chron. pag. 192. <hi>num.</hi> MMLXIX.</note> beginning of <hi>Nero</hi>'s Reign, but alſo in the time of his Predeceſſor <hi>Claudius</hi> (as <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> doth <note n="¶" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Joſeph. Antiq. Judaic. <hi>lib.</hi> 19. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 20. <hi>c.</hi> 1, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7. <hi>Item de bello</hi> Judaic. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 20, 21, 22, 23. <hi>Vide &amp;</hi> Euſeb. Hiſt. Eccleſ. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 21.</note> acknowledg the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, took up a mortal and flaming haued againſt the Chriſtians, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing them to be as troubleſom and as the reſt,</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:39423:8"/>
            <p> But when <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> came to the Throne (that Humane and Good-natured Prince, who was wont to weep even at the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Caeterum neque caede cujuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam laetatus, juſtis ſupplicis illachrymavit etiam &amp; inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuit.</hi> Suet. <hi>in</hi> Veſpaſian. §. 13.</note> Juſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of Criminals) all Bloudy proceedings againſt our Religion were ſtopt. For he had been at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in Perſon; and having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved there the vaſt difference between the Turbulent and Obſtinate temper of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the Peaceable behaviour of the Chriſtians, he was particularly Favourable and Kind to theſe: So that though he had Ruined the <hi>Jews</hi> (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> obſerves) and though he ſtrictly ſearched after all the Royal Poſterity of <hi>David,</hi> with a deſign to take them off (as <note n="¶" place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>Hiſt. Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> tells us) yet both thoſe Ancient Writers do agree <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>—Nullus</hi> Veſpaſianus, <hi>quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis Judaeorum debellator, &amp;c.</hi> Tertul. <hi>Apol. Cap.</hi> 6.</note> that he <note place="margin">—<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Euſeb. <hi>Hist. Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 17.</note> uſed no manner of Severity to wards the Chriſtian Profeſſion.</p>
            <p>The next cruel Emperour was <hi>Domitian;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Domitianus, <hi>portio</hi> Neronius <hi>de credulitate,</hi> Tertul. <hi>Apol. cap.</hi> 5.</note> a limb of <hi>Nero</hi> (as <hi>Tertulian</hi> calls him) that not only baniſht St. <hi>John</hi> into <hi>Patmos,</hi> but miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly vexed the whole Chriſtian Church. The Occaſion of his barbarity was no other then <hi>Herods</hi> fear, that Chriſt would come, and take his Empire from him; which fear was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed by a falſe ſuggeſtion, touching the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Spirits of Chriſts Diſciples. But lighting happily upon ſome of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Euſeb. Hiſt. Eccleſ. lib. 3. <hi>c.</hi> 20. <hi>Sed q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia homo, facile caeptum repreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit, reſtitutis etiam quos relligaverat, iniquit</hi> Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullianus <hi>de</hi> Domitiano.</note> them, and (as they ſay) ſome of our Bleſſed Saviours own Kindred; and finding upon examination, that they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:39423:8"/> were a plain and honeſt ſort of Men, that paid Tribute, and wrought diligently in their vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation with their own hands, and lived quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and hoped for no Kingdom but that in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother world; he ſtraight gave over his ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, being fully ſatisfied, that Chriſtians were followers of that which was Good.</p>
            <p>Hence on to the time of <hi>Trajan,</hi> we hear no more of the Chriſtians ſufferings. Then indeed the Inſtruments of death were uſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh againſt them, upon the old ſtale pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, that they were Evil doers. But <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> writing to <hi>Trajan</hi> was ſo juſt to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide Ep.</hi> Plinii Trajano, <hi>&amp;</hi> Trajani Plinio; Plin. <hi>Ep. l.</hi> 10. <hi>Item</hi> Tertul. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pol. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.</note> that he told the Emperour, all he found by the Chriſtians was, that on a certain day they were wont to meet together, and Sing Hymns to Chriſt, and bound themſelves by a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not to be guilty of Thefts, or Robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, or Adultery, or breach of Faith, nor of any other Crime. Whereupon <hi>Trajan</hi> orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that the inquiſition againſt Chriſtians ſhould be preſently ſtopt; and ſo the Rage of that time went ſoon off, when 'twas diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red what a good ſort of Men the Chriſtians were.</p>
            <p>Then came the Emperor <hi>Adrian,</hi> who, tho' he made no <note n="¶" place="margin">Tertul. Apol. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> new Edicts againſt the Chriſtians, yet permitted thoſe that were to <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quarta ſub</hi> Adriano <hi>perjecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio numeratur;</hi> Sulp. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</note> be put in force, ſuppoſing (as others before him did) that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were a troubleſome and intra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:39423:9"/> Sect, eſpecially upon that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion of the <hi>Jews,</hi> which fell out in the beginning of <hi>Adrians</hi> govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <note place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>in</hi> Chronico.</note> But when <hi>Ariſtides</hi> and <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dratus</hi> had preſented their Excellent Apologies to him, he found that he had been deceived in his Opinion, and ſo proceedings were preſently mitiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for he wrote a Letter to <hi>Minu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius Fundanus</hi> the Proconſul of <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Juſt. Martyr. Apolog <hi>p.</hi> 99 <hi>&amp;</hi> 100. <hi>Item</hi> Apol Melitonis <hi>in</hi> Euſeb. Hiſt. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. lib.</note> 
               <hi>Aſia,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Aelius Lamprid. <hi>in</hi> vit. Alex<hi>:</hi> Sever.</note> and to many more of his Officers in ſeveral other parts of the VVorld, requiring them to deal mildly with Chriſtians, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending ſuch as wrongfully brought them into Trouble. Nay one <hi>Pagan</hi> Hiſtorian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of this Emperor <hi>Adrian, that himſelf built a Temple and dedicated it unto Chriſt, and Worſhipt him as a God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To go on further, afterwards in the Reign of <hi>Antoninus Pius,</hi> though here and there di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Poſt</hi> Adria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anum Antoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Pio <hi>impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rante, pax Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is fuit,</hi> Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit. Sever. <hi>lib.</hi> 2.</note> Chriſtians ſuffered by the officious malice of ſome inferiour Miniſters of State; yet that merciful and Generous Prince (who was wont to ſay, <hi>He had rather ſave one Citizen, than kill a Thouſand Enemies)</hi> ſoon reſtored Peace unto the Church. The reaſon was, becauſe that great Luminary of the Church <hi>Juſtin</hi> the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, and at laſt a Martyr, wrote an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Apology to <hi>Antoninus,</hi> and the whole Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate complaining of the injuſtice of proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and ſhewing the innocence of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians Doctrines, Rites, and Lives. Upon
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:39423:9"/> which the Emperor being now ſatisfied, that thoſe men were followers of that which was good, did in a Letter to the Common Council of <hi>Aſia,</hi> and to all the Greeks (which is yet extant) ſharply blame his Officers for their raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and ordered, that no Chriſtian ſhould ſuffer more, unleſs he attempted the diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of the Empire; which he was morally aſſured, no true Chriſtian would go about.</p>
            <p>Indeed his Succeſſor <hi>Aurelius Antoninus</hi> moſt grievouſly afflicted the Church in ſeveral pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Juſtin. Apol. <hi>in fine.</hi> Euſeb. Hiſt. <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 5 Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tul. Apolog. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> of the Empire. For new accuſations were invented; and therefore New Edicts were publiſht againſt them. But all this while even that Emperor ſeem'd to have been miſtaken concerning the Church; for it is not credible that a perſon of ſuch great worth as <hi>Antoxinus</hi> was of (being an exquiſite Philoſopher, and a Stoick) would have been ſo cruel to good men; but would have ſpared them at leaſt, for common Morality and Virtue ſake, had he been ſatisfied of their Integrity. However, when S. <hi>Melito, Apolonaris, Athenagoras,</hi> and ſome more, open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vindicated themſelves and their Brethren, and deſired nothing but that Juſtice might be done them, it had a mighty Effect and Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon the Emperor; though nothing wrought on him ſo much as the Miraculous Rain which fell at the Prayers of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, when he and his Army were in the bowels of <hi>Germany</hi> ready to periſh for want of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:39423:10"/> Water: then he was Convinced, that God was with the Chriſtians; and ſo ſet out an Edict, that they ſhould be kindly uſed for the future, and that whoſoever ſhould accuſe a Chriſtian only under the Notion of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian (as if that were Crime enough) ſhould be burnt alive.</p>
            <p>And ſo the courſe of the World went tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerably well, till <hi>Severus</hi> gat into the Throne; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Severo vide</hi> Tertul. ad Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulam.</note> nay indeed for ſome time after<hi>:</hi> For at firſt he was very favourable to our Religion, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſome Knowledge of it, and a kind Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of its Profeſſors. For (as we are told by <hi>Tertullian,</hi> who flouriſht in his time) he entertained one <hi>Proculus,</hi> a Chriſtian in his own Palace, and was not diſpleaſed though he knew, that <hi>Proculus</hi> inſtructed his Son <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninus Caracalla</hi> in the Chriſtian Religion; he was gracious to many of the <hi>Roman</hi> Nobility, whom he knew to be Chriſtians, and protected them from the Rage and fury of the populace. 'Twas pitty indeed he did not go on, when he was in ſo good a way; but the truth is, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great men there were, that were pertina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly addicted to Heathen Superſtition and Idolatry, and never left raiſing and carrying of lies to his Ears againſt the Chriſtians; and he believing them upon their report, became quite another man, if <hi>I</hi> may ſo call that Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Wretch; vvhich provoked <hi>Tertullian</hi> to write his admirable Apology; wherein he vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:39423:10"/> the honour of our Religion, and the innocence of its profeſſors; which tho' it had little effect upon <hi>Severus</hi> himſelf, yet it had upon his Son <hi>Caracalla,</hi> ſo that his Reign vvas peaceable, as his Succeſſors was too; till <hi>Maximinus</hi> made foul Work again<hi>:</hi> But we need not wonder at him; for he vvas a man of ſordid Birth, and Brutiſh inclinations; firſt a Shepheard, then a Robber upon the High ways, next a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, and at laſt a Prince forſooth, though a Prince that would underſtand nothing but Arts of wickedneſs, and therefore deſerves <note place="margin">Tert. Apol. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> to ſtand by himſelf. If you reckon from <hi>Nero</hi> downward, you will find <hi>Tertullians</hi> Obſervation True, that of all the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors to his time, there was none that had any ordinary regard for Natural Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion or Humanity, who offered violence to the Chriſtians; when once they through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcovered what the Nature of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, and the temper of Chriſtians was.</p>
            <p>And the ſame Obſervation I might pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue further on ſtill, even to the days of <hi>Conſtantine;</hi> had I time to do it, and were the thing neceſſary, after what has been ſhew'd already. For ſtill as our Religion appeared (I ſay induſtriouſly, Our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for that which was then the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical and Catholick Religion there, is ours now; as it appeared) in its Native Beauty:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:39423:11"/> it ever commanded, firſt the Pity, then the protection, and at laſt the Love of all that had Souls, of all that had any value for Virtue and honour, till in the end Princes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were enamour'd with it, and count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Croſs the Nobleſt Ornaments of their Crowns and Scepters.</p>
            <p>3. But I ſhall not make any more Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Obſervations, preſuming that theſe few are ſufficient for the confirmation of the point in hand. VVhence I ſhall novv by vvay of application of this vvhole matter, put that queſtion of the Apoſtles in the Text vvith reference to our ſelves, And vvho is he that vvill harm us, if vve be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovvers of that vvhich is good? Had the Primitive Chriſtians, been of ſome mens temper; had they taken ſuch a proſpect of times, as ſome among us are ready to take, whoſe fears are apt to reach as far as the VVorlds end; 'tis a wonder if they had not anſwer'd St. <hi>Peter</hi> thus, <hi>Nero</hi> will undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly hurt us, and ſo may <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> and <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> too, nay <hi>Conſtantine</hi> himſelf, for ought we know, to be ſure ſuch a one will, if we be not ſo Politick as to exclude him before hand, and provide ſome ſtrong Aſſociation in time. But this vvas not their Temper, nor St. <hi>Peters</hi> Jealouſie: All that he had to direct them, and all that they had to take care of, vvas this, to be follovvers ſtill of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:39423:11"/> that which was good, and to follow it ſo, as to approve themſelves to God, and to the VVorld, to make it plain and manifeſt, that Vertue and a good Conſcience was their whole ſtudy; this, this was that, which carried them out, which ſupported the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Religion, which ſecur'd its Intereſt, which made it lovely, ſtable, proſperous, even in times of Heatheniſm.</p>
            <p>Now if we too take this Chriſtian, this Prudent and effectual courſe, who is he that will go about to annoy us? Little Troubles indeed we muſt never expect to be free from as long as the VVorld ſtandeth: For the Church of Chriſt hath ever been vexed with ſome Briers or other, ſome Thorns have ever been in its ſides; nor hath Our Church been without them; we have had ſome Brambles of our own growth, that have made our Church not only ſmart, but bleed too: Nay, we have had ſuch of late, as like that Bramble in the parable, <hi>Jud.</hi> 9. would in all haſte have been Reigning over us, and would have devoured all the great Trees in <hi>Lebanon.</hi> Perhaps we may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be free from thoſe ſcratching, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible Shrubs as long as the old Curſe continues upon the Earth; ſome or other may ſtill be ſpringing up among us: But the Church can never dye of a Thorn; nor can ſuch paultry things do us any conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:39423:12"/> injury, eſpecially when they are over dropt by the Tall Cedars; while we ſhall be protected under their ſhaddow, if we do but know and adorn our Station, and grow in Grace, and be manifeſtly and plainly mindful of that which is good.</p>
            <p>What hard Uſages did yet Primitive Chriſtians undergo, who were taught, not with Briers and Thorns only, as the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion is, <hi>Jude</hi> 8. but with Harrows and and Axes too? And yet you ſee what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice was given them here in the Text; and becauſe experience and matter of Fact is ſuch a ſtrong argument. I have particularly ſhew'd you how ſucceſsful that advice was, and even in thoſe moſt diſcouraging times, when Tyranny was the Government, and Paganiſm was the Religion of the VVorld.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed for ever, bleſſed be God, this is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely far from being any part of our Caſe; Nay, but that ſome love to be ungrateful both to God and Man, methinks we ſhould all look upon our ſelves as obliged (I am ſure, we are highly bound) to tender Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven our moſt hearty Thanks, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all our High and Monſtrous Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations (that which is proper for us al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to conſider and think of) God is ſtill ſo propitious to us, as that we have a very fair proſpect, touching the ſecurity not of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:39423:12"/> our Perſons and Fortunes only, but of that too, which is and ought to be, far dearer to us than our very Lives; I mean, our Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht and incomparable Religion.</p>
            <p>Having therefore ſuch encouragements, and thoſe grounded upon ſuch Foundations, let us, in the Name of God, once more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the directions in the Text, and ſhew our ſelves ſtill hearty followers of that which is good. We may be ſure no valuable inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry can be done us, if we our ſelves be but careful to do Our part; that which is both our Duty and intereſt to do. Therefore inſtead of leaping over our Line, to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our ſelves and the VVorld with inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Fears, let us ſeriouſly apply our minds to our Buſineſs, our proper and neceſſary buſineſs; not doubting, but that which ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſo to carry out the Old Chriſtians, will ſerve much more, to ſecure us, not from Calamity only, but even from danger of it<hi>:</hi> Two things eſpecially were unjuſtly laid to their Charge, <hi>viz.</hi> that their Religion was New, and that they themſelves were wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: When once theſe two points were fully cleared, Sovereign Princes became not their Friends only, but their fellovv Chriſtians too.</p>
            <p>Novv as to the firſt of theſe (an accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, vvhich hath been unjuſtly laid to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:39423:13"/> Our charge too) vve have made it abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly evident to all ſober and teachable, though prejudiced perſons, that our Faith is that vvhich vvas once for all delivered unto the Saints. This vve vvill for ever a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide by, this vve vvill be bound to make evident ſtill. But if men vvill not ſee our Evidence, vve confeſs it is not in our povv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to vvork ſuch a Miracle, as to put eyes into the blind, and force them to ſee, vvhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they vvill or no; and yet I cannot tell, but time and Conſtancy may do even that too, as it did in the former Ages of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>As Our Faith is manifeſtly Pure, Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and Apoſtolical; ſo let us do it that Honour and Right (novv eſpecially) as to make it plain and Evident to the World, that our manners are ſuitable thereunto. This vvas the Great Evidence that in anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent times did by degrees ſo affectually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the Enemies of our Religion; for by obſerving the Excellent Lives of Chriſtians, they vvere Naturally led firſt to a ſearch, then to an Admiration, and in the end to the profeſſion of our Doctrines, and by theſe means our Religion came not only to a quiet, but to a Regnant condition in the World.</p>
            <p>For your imitation and Encouragement
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:39423:13"/> in this Caſe, ſhall I now at the cloſe of this Diſcourſe tell you, what thoſe good things were, which were then ſo taking and ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in their Eyes? Why, in ſhort it was this; an entire, ſincere, and Univerſal Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the precepts of Chriſtianity. St. <hi>Paul</hi> hath drawn up all into a ſhort Summa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in <hi>Philip.</hi> 4. A place, where he adviſed the <hi>Philippians</hi> to be careful for nothing, mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the things of this World, which the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of men are apt to be moſt careful for: <hi>Be careful for nothing,</hi> ver. 6. and then he adds, ver. 8. <hi>Finally, Brethren, whatſoever things are true, whatſoever things are Honeſt, whatſoever things are Juſt, whatſoever things are Pure, whatſoever things are lovely, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever things are of Good Report; if there be any Vertue, if there be any Praiſe, think on theſe things.</hi> Theſe things the Primitive Chriſtians had learned, and received, and heard, and ſeen in the Holy Apoſtles; as it follows there; and as they did and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticed theſe things, ſo the God of Peace, was ſtill with them, till he made their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Enemies to be at Peace with them alſo.</p>
            <p>Yet by the Hiſtory of thoſe times I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that there were ſome ſpecial and particular Vertues which the <hi>Pagans</hi> took great notice of, and were induced to be very favourable and kind to the Chriſtians for. As <hi>Severus</hi> the Emperour was exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:39423:14"/> pleaſed with that Command of our Bleſſed Saviours, ſo that he had it engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved upon his Plates, Whatſoever ye would that men ſhould do unto you, even ſo do you unto them: In like manner other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were pleas'd and taken with ſome ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Remarks in the Lives of Chriſts fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, which they obſerved perhaps above other things, becauſe they did moſt conduce to the Honour, and intereſt, and peace of their Government: And theſe were the things, The Primitive Chriſtians were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diligent and honeſt in their ſeveral Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings; they minded their own buſineſs, not medling with matters that were out of their Sphear, eſpecially with the buſineſs of their Governours: They ſtudied to be quiet, and as much as in them lay, lived peaceably with all men: They were juſt in their deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with all men; and very Candid, and charitable in their cenſures of their Rulers. They abhorred that Villanous Practice of ſuſpecting and reviling Magiſtrates: They were afraid for Conſcience ſake to raiſe and diſperſe lies, to render Princes odious; but did ever put the kindeſt Conſtructions upon their Counſels and proceedings, that they were capable of. They would not by any means affront them, or contumeliouſly uſe them, or ſpeak evil of them, or pray back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for them (I mean, pray for their i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l fortune or ruine, as ſome peſtilent Men
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:39423:14"/> would now adays make us believe) no they behaved themſelves towards them (though mortal Enemies to their Faith) with modeſty and reverence, and all due reſpect. They paid them their Tribute Mony honeſtly; they ſerved them in their Wars with all Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Courage. If any thing was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of them, which was inconſiſtent with a good Conſcience, and the Laws of Chriſt, they would decline it indeed, even unto Death, but ſtill with tenderneſs, and a Religious regard to the Honour and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Emperor. They lookt upon him as Gods immediate Miniſter, next to God, and ſubject only unto him, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore unaccountable to any in this world; and accordingly they feared, and honoured, nay loved him, becauſe he was Gods De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty here below, and in the Earth Supreme. They never went to their Devotion, but the Emperor had a great ſhare of it; and even when times were ominous and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, then too they would pray for his Health, and long life, for Victory in his Arms, and for his wellfare and good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs in all his juſt Undertakings. As for reſiſtance, they deteſted and diſclaimed the very thoughts of it, ſo that they would ſuffer themſelves to be cut in pieces rather than they would rebel, though ſeveral Laws were on their ſide, and they had the Sword in their Hands, and had ſtrength
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:39423:15"/> and Forces enough to to make the whole Empire tremble. In all lawful inſtances, none more ready to obey, none more faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in their obedience; but in other Caſes, none ſo willing to dye at their Princes Feet, as the Chriſtians were.</p>
            <p>Theſe are ſome of thoſe things which are honeſt, and juſt, and pure, and lovely, and of good report; and by following theſe good things, the World was at laſt ſatisfied, that they were good men; and ſo the Church by degrees wrought it ſelf out of thoſe difficulties and hardſhips, which it felt and lay under, when our Religion firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the World.</p>
            <p>Happy ſhall we be now, if like the Old Chriſtians, we be thus followers of that which is Good; ſo that all men may ſee, and be convinced that we are ſo. This is that which will be a ſecurity to our Church an Honour to our Religion, a Comfort and ſatisfaction, as well as a ſecurity to our ſelves<hi>:</hi> 'Tis that which will not only bring Peace to us in this Life, but will bring us all to thoſe unſpeakable Joys and Comforts in another, where infinity of pleaſure is laid up in ſtore, as the endleſs portion of all thoſe Bleſſed Souls, that Love the Lord Jeſus in ſincerity.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:39423:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
